Hua Zhen?
华桢
Did he come from Nanjing
那他是从南京
to Shanghai?
来上海的吗
Miss Shi,
石老师
how did you know?
你怎么知道
Zhang,
老张
could you wait for me downstairs for a moment?
你先到楼下等我一下吧
Miss Shi,
石老师你看
take a look at my homework.
我写的作业
I didn't expect
没想到
you'd assign homework to Duoci.
你还给多慈布置了作业
I finish it on time every day.
我每天都按时完成呢
Officer Xiang,
向警官
you already know
我是督察员的身份
I'm an inspector.
你已经知道了
I'm also
我也是
a friend of Mr. and Mrs. Meng,
孟先生孟太太的朋友
and Duoci's French teacher.
是多慈的法语老师
I wasn't in Shanghai when Duoci's parents
多慈父母出事的时候
had the accident.
我不在上海
Thank you for taking her in.
谢谢你收留了她
Now that I'm back,
现在我回来了
Duoci is safe with me
多慈可以放心地交给我
and you may return to Nanjing
你也可以回南京
and your life.
继续你的生活
She paid me for a month
她花钱雇了我一个月
to find the killer for her.
替她找凶手
So I won't leave.
我就不可能提前离开
Besides, I don't trust you enough
更何况我不信任你
to leave her with you.
不可能把她交给你的
Actually, this was also
其实这也是
a request from Duoci's parents before they died.
多慈父母生前的嘱托
Mr. and Mrs. Meng hoped
孟先生和孟太太希望
that, if they
他们不能
couldn't take care of Duoci,
照顾多慈的时候
I would take her to Hong Kong
我能把她送到香港
to continue her life.
继续生活
I respect her own will.
我尊重她的意愿
But if she doesn't want to go,
但如果她不愿意走
you can't
你就不可能
take her away.
把她从我身边带走
Officer Xiang,
向警官
I know many of
孟先生和孟太太的朋友
Mr. and Mrs. Meng's friends, too.
我也认识不少
Can you tell me
你可以告诉我
who asked you to bring this book
是谁托你把这本书
to Shanghai?
送到上海的吗
Miss Shi,
石小姐
you're just her French teacher.
你只是她的法语老师
Aren't you
你管得
being a bit too nosy?
是不是太多了一点儿
I'm also an inspector
我也是公董局
with the Concession Municipal Council.
警务处的督察员
The victims
现在遇害的
were my friends
是我的朋友
and important taxpayers
也是法租界的
of the French Concession.
重要纳税人
Personally and officially,
于公于私
I am very concerned about this case.
我确实很关心这个案子
I came to the council for
我去公董局找你谈判
the Meng family's case.
是为了孟家的案子
But business is business.
但一码事儿归一码事儿
That doesn't mean
这不代表
I'll exchange
我会用自己的私事儿
personal favors.
交换
And,
还有
Duoci now goes by Qiushi,
多慈现在叫秋实
Li Qiushi,
黎秋实
so don't get it wrong.
别再叫错了
Duoci,
多慈
are you sure not to go with me?
你真的不跟我离开吗
Miss Shi,
石老师
let me stay for one more month.
你就再让我留一个月吧
After that,
等一个月后
when Yuansheng goes back to Nanjing,
远生哥哥回南京了
I'll follow you to Hong Kong.
我就听你的 去香港
But can he
可是这一个月
take good care of you in this month?
他确定能照顾好你吗
He has been
远生哥哥
taking very good care of me.
已经把我照顾得很好了
Looks like
看来以后
I'll have to start calling you Li Qiushi from now on.
我要改口叫你黎秋实了
I don't welcome any visitors
我不欢迎任何人
who come by like you again,
再以这样的方式来做客
and I hope
也希望
this is the last time you follow me.
这是你最后一次跟踪我
Sorry about today,
今天的事情很抱歉
but I think
但我想我们
we both want
保护秋实的目的
to protect Qiushi.
是一样的
And I've already
另外 我今天已经
requested the Police Service
向警务处提出申请
to drop the complaint against The Fourth Station House.
撤销对四所的投诉
They agreed so.
他同意了
With the complaint gone,
投诉撤销之后
their penalties
四所的处分
will be lifted, too.
也很快就会被撤销
Since Qiushi wants to stay,
既然秋实想要留在这里
please take good
那也拜托你
care of her.
好好照顾她
She's not coming with us?
孩子不跟我们走吗
She wants to stay.
她想留在这儿
I'm worried that forcing her
我怕硬把她带走
might cause trouble.
出什么变故
Zhang,
老张
rent a house nearby
你在附近租个房子
to keep an eye on things here
看好这边
and ensure her safety.
一定要保护好孩子
Understood.
好 知道了
Like this,
是这样
got it?
明白了吗
Got it.
明白了
Hello?
喂
I'll be back within a month,
最迟一个月
no matter what.
无论如何都会回来
Brother, is everything alright back home?
哥 家里还好吗
I'm calling
我给你打电话
because everyone at home
就是要跟你说这件事情
was called in
家里的所有人
by the Party Investigation Dept.
都去党务调查处
for questioning.
接受问询了
[They didn't even]
连家里的佣人
[spare our servants.]
都没有放过
[They've sent someone]
他们现在已经派人
[to Shanghai for you.]
去上海找你了
[Get ready to be scrutinized.]
你等着接受审查吧
[You've had private dealings]
毕竟你和邓铭远
[with Deng Mingyuan.]
私下里接触过
[Just answer their questions.]
你就正常回答问题就行
[Don't elaborate.]
别多说
[Unless they find something concrete,]
除非他们抓到什么把柄
[they shouldn't hassle]
不然不会为难
[our family.]
我们家的人
[Come in.]
进
Deng Mingyuan sent you a book.
邓铭远送了一本书给你
Right.
对
Which book?
什么书
Die entscheidenden Momente der Menschheit.
人类的选择时刻
He gave you a gift,
他送给你礼物
yet he didn't also ask you for a favor?
就没有顺便托你帮忙
What kind of favor?
帮什么忙
Like, helping him leave Nanjing
比如托你帮他离开南京
or come to Shanghai
或者来上海
to handle things.
帮忙办某件事
No.
没有
Then why did you suddenly show up in Shanghai?
那你为什么突然来上海
The military academy rarely gives us breaks.
军校很少放假
I wanted to explore Shanghai during my time off.
我想趁假期在上海逛逛
[You were alone with Deng Mingyuan in the study.]
你和邓铭远单独在书房
[Did you talk about]
除了聊
[anything other than]
有关海军方面的书
[naval books?]
还有别的吗
No.
没有
Think hard.
你再想想
Don't leave anything out.
千万别遗漏
I did ask him
我向老师
about something.
打听了一件事情
What's that?
什么事
In 1924,
民国十三年
the former Premier traveled north
先总理从广州
on the Yongfeng-class Gunboat from Guangzhou,
登永丰舰北上
and Deng was the Second Mate.
老师是船上的二副
I asked him
我向他打听
what food the Premier liked
先总理在船上
aboard the ship.
喜欢吃什么
Does that count?
这算吗
Mr. Hua.
华先生
my name is Zheng Yudong,
我姓郑 郑于栋
formerly with the Ministry of Military Affairs' Navy Dept.
以前是军政部海军署的
Your family took good care of me
我在军政部的时候呢
while I was there.
受过您家人的关照
So, I'll just
所以这件事儿
want to tell you that
我就冒昧地劝你一句
you're young.
你还年轻
Make sure you keep a clear line
务必跟邓铭远
between you and Deng Mingyuan
还有和他相关的人
and his associates.
划清界限
You're from the Navy Dept.,
您是海军署的
surely you
对邓先生为人的
know Mr. Deng
了解程度
better than
应该远胜于
my family, right?
对我的家人吧
Qiushi,
秋实
I'm back with breakfast.
我买早饭回来了
I'm here.
我在这里呢
What's up?
你怎么了
Yuansheng,
远生哥哥
can you braid my hair?
你会编辫子吗
Me?
我
Yeah.
对
I'm not as good as you.
我还不如你
No worries, let's just eat then.
没关系 那咱们吃饭吧
Does it have to be a braid?
一定要编成辫子吗
Mom used to braid it for me.
以前都是妈妈给我编的
I think braids are pretty.
我觉得辫子很漂亮
Let's eat first.
先吃饭吧
After we're done,
吃完饭
I'll take you somewhere.
我带你去个地方
Luo...
骆
Yuansheng,
远生哥哥
are we in the wrong place?
咱们是来错地方了吗
What do you need?
你找我有什么事儿
Officer Luo,
骆警官
sorry to bother you.
打扰了
I need your advice on something.
有件事儿想向你请教
Luo Minmin,
骆珉敏
you're stealing my hot water again!
你又抢我热水
What's it to you?
抢你热水怎么了
I boiled this water!
这是我烧的热水
You're not even working!
你又没工作
Who says I'm not working?
谁说我没工作
Dad!
爸
Luo Minmin is going to hit me!
骆珉敏要打我
I'm telling you,
我告诉你
you're just spoiled.
你现在就是被我惯得
Disrespectful!
没大没小
Say it. What do you want?
你说吧 你什么事儿
Miss,
姐姐
can you braid hair?
你会编辫子吗
Braid hair?
编辫子
Of course, I can.
我当然会了
My sister wants her hair braided,
我妹妹想编辫子
but I can't do it.
但是我不会
I couldn't find
我在上海
anyone else in Shanghai
也实在找不到其他人
to help.
能帮这个忙了
Officer Luo,
骆警官
could you braid her hair
你能帮她编一个
neatly for her?
整齐点的辫子吗
Officer Xiang,
向警官
it's nine in the morning.
现在是早上九点钟
If you weren't out there arresting people in the French Concession,
要不是你去法租界抓人
I would be at the Fourth Station
我现在应该刚好在四所
doing my job as a cop,
好好地当我的警察
not here fighting over
而不是在这儿
hot water with my sister.
跟我妹妹抢热水
Besides,
再说了
we're not even close,
我们俩又不熟
but your sister...
你妹妹
have big eyes.
眼睛还挺大的
Come on in.
进来吧
Luo Minmin is stealing my hot water again!
骆珉敏又抢我热水
And she even threw a slipper at me!
她还拿拖鞋砸我
Aren't you going to do something?
你管不管
Your sister just got suspended.
你姐刚刚停职
Don't provoke her.
你别招惹她
Be nice.
乖嘛
Dad!
爸
My friend is here!
我朋友来家里了
Coming!
来了
This is Officer Xiang,
这是向警官
my colleague from the Fourth Station House.
我四所的同事
Officer Xiang, this is my father,
向警官 这是我父亲
and this is my sister.
这是我妹妹
I'm Luo Qinqin,
我叫骆勤芹
the first "qin" for diligent, and the second for celery.
勤劳的勤 芹菜的芹
Sorry to disturb you.
不好意思 打扰了
Not at all.
不打扰 不打扰
Welcome.
欢迎 欢迎 欢迎
I'm back.
我回来了
Do we have guests?
这家里来客人了
This is my brother, Luo Tianxiang.
这是我哥哥骆天祥
And this is Officer Xiang.
这是向警官
Officer Xiang.
向警官
Alright,
好了
I'll take you upstairs, okay?
我带你上去好不好
Wait here for me.
你在这儿等我吧
Go clean the fish.
去把鱼处理一下
I'll cook it in a bit.
我一会儿要做
Officer Xiang,
向警官
please, have a seat.
快坐 快坐 快坐
I'll go check on my sister.
我去看看我姐
Sit.
坐 坐 坐
Split it into three parts,
把它分成三股
then move the right strand to the center,
然后右边的放到中间
and then the left to the center,
左边的也放到中间
keep repeating, just keep repeating.
一直重复 重复
You keep doing that until the end.
一直重复到最后就好了
Didn't your mom
那你在家的时候
braid your hair when you were at home?
妈妈不会给你扎辫子吗
My parents
我爸爸妈妈
aren't in Shanghai.
他们不在上海
That's okay.
没关系的
Look at my sister.
你看我妹妹
I taught her
从小到大
how to braid from a young age,
辫子都是我教她的
and she picked it up right away.
一学就会
You're smart.
你那么聪明
You'll learn how.
肯定也能学会
Thank you, sister.
那就谢谢姐姐啦
I'll head downstairs.
我先下去了
Look at her,
你看
all grown up but still acts
这么大了 还没长大呢
like a little kid.
小孩儿
You and my daughter
你和我女儿
work at the Fourth Station House?
在四所做事
Yes.
对
What's your name?
叫什么名字
Xiang Yuansheng.
向远生
And how old?
多大了
Married yet?
成家了吗
Dad,
爸
he's our guest.
人家是客人
Can't I even talk now?
我还不能说话了
If personal questions are off-limits,
私事不问
I'll stick to work-related ones.
那我就问公事
Are you the boss over there?
你是四所的长官
No,
不是
I'm just another new officer,
我和骆警官一样
like Luo.
是新警员
What do you need my daughter for?
你找我女儿干什么
It's actually my sister who needed
是我妹妹有事儿
Officer Luo's help.
找骆警官帮忙
Sorry to bother you.
打扰您了
No problem at all.
不不不
As long as it's not about work,
只要不是四所的事儿
you're not bothering us.
就不打扰
Heard you all got penalized?
听说你们四所被罚了
Does that mean you can't be cops anymore?
是不是当不了警察了
The decision isn't final yet.
这事儿还没有最后决定
But it looks like we might not be suspended.
不过应该有可能不停职
What?
什么
Not suspended?
不罚了
So,
那
you're always hanging around with Xiang Yuansheng?
你一直跟着向远生哥哥
He's my cousin.
他是我表哥
Can he take good care of a kid?
那他能照顾好小孩儿吗
Absolutely.
能啊
All done with the braid.
好了 扎好了
Let me check.
我看看
It looks beautiful!
真漂亮
Why are these sleeves so big?
你这袖子怎么这么大
Who bought you this outfit?
这衣服谁给你买的
Yuansheng.
远生哥哥
Wait,
不是
why isn't there a penalty anymore?
为什么不罚了呢
Weren't you supposed to get punished?
不是说好了要罚的吗
What happened to that?
为什么现在不罚了
You know, you cops
你说你们这些警察吧
never keep your word.
没有一个说话算话的
Who's sticking their nose where it doesn't belong?
谁这么多管闲事儿啊
It's so irritating!
怎么那么讨厌呢
Dad, why are you bringing this up?
爸 你说这些干什么呀
Come with me for a second.
跟我过来一趟
What kind of brother are you?
你这哥哥怎么当的
What did I do wrong?
我怎么了
Her parents aren't around,
她父母既然不在身边
and as her brother,
由你这个哥哥照顾
you should be properly looking after her.
你就应该好好照顾
How can you take care of her
你什么都不懂
if you know nothing?
怎么照顾啊
Because I can't braid hair?
因为我不会扎辫子
Obviously not.
当然不是
Is it because she's
那是因为长身体
not eating right,
营养不够
or not drinking enough milk?
还是因为牛奶喝少了
Do you think you're raising a kitten?
你以为你在养小猫啊
She said
你妹妹说
her parents have gone far away,
她父母去了很远的地方
and now it's just her with you,
现在她就一个人跟着你
right?
对吗
Right.
对
So she won't see
那她岂不是很长时间
her parents
都见不到
for a long time?
自己的爸爸妈妈了
Right.
对
She's sad
她觉得难过
not because
不是因为
she can't braid her hair.
她自己不会扎辫子
At this age, girls start
虽然女孩子
to care about
都是这个年纪
looking nice,
开始爱美的
but it's because...
那是因为
other girls
别的女孩子
have their moms to braid their hair
都有妈妈扎辫子
for them,
她没有
and she misses her parents.
她想爸爸妈妈了
If her parents
如果她以后
aren't around in the future,
父母都不在身边
especially her mom,
特别是妈妈不在身边
you're going to encounter
你照顾她
a lot of challenges caring for her.
还会遇到很多很多问题
If you really want
如果你真的想要
to look after her well,
好好照顾她
you need to be attentive.
就得用心
Pay close attention.
用心地观察
How do you know all this?
你怎么知道这些
My sister was four
我妹妹四岁的时候
when our mom got sick and died.
妈妈生病离开了
I was eight that year.
那年我八岁
So, I know.
所以我知道
Did you get
我刚跟你说这些
all that?
你懂了吧
Now I do.
现在懂了
It doesn't help much
你懂了也没有用
if you're dressing her in clothes
你看你给她穿的衣服
that don't fit.
一点也不合身
Can't believe
真不知道你考试
you aced two of your exams.
还怎么两门满分的
She's still practicing her braiding.
你妹妹还在练习扎辫子
Just sit here and wait,
你就在这儿坐着等着吧
so my dad
免得我爸
doesn't start on you again.
又跟你胡说八道
Sit down.
坐着呀
Sit tight here,
你在这儿坐好了
don't touch anything,
别瞎碰东西
don't mess around,
别乱动
and don't talk to anyone.
也别跟人说话
Got it?
记住了吧
Got it.
记住了
Didn't I tell you not to stare?
不是叫你不要乱看吗
Dad, didn't you say
爸 你不是说
you put it away?
收起来了吗
Why is it out again?
怎么又挂出来了
I thought you liked this one.
你不是说这张好看吗
All set now.
系上就好了
Three...
三
two...
二
wait, hold on a second...
等会儿 等会儿 等会儿
Wait a moment.
等会儿 等会儿
One.
一
So beautiful.
好漂亮啊
That's the deal.
那就这么说定了啊
Brother.
远生哥哥
Look.
你看
I can braid my own hair.
我自己会编辫子了
From now on,
以后
Your sister is smart.
你妹妹特别聪明
Like my sister Luo Qinqin,
像我妹妹骆勤芹一样
she's a quick learner.
学东西特别快
Ms. Luo,
骆警官
thank you.
谢谢你
Let's go.
我们走吧
All right.
好吧
I'll walk you out.
那我送你们到门口吧
[Qinqin, I don't have enough eggs.]
勤芹 我鸡蛋不够
[Get two more for me.]
你再 再帮我拿两个
[Brother, take it yourself.]
哥 你自己拿去吧
[I'm busy peeling garlic.]
你看我这忙着剥蒜呢
[I don't have time for that.]
没空
[It's just peeling garlic.]
剥个蒜那能费啥劲
[Nonsense.]
你也真是
Do you have food at home?
你们家有人做饭吗
We'll go to a restaurant.
我们去饭馆吃
Goodbye
那就不打扰了
Wait a minute.
等会儿
Do you want to eat vegetable congee?
你想不想吃菜泡饭
What is that?
菜泡饭是什么
It's a kind of congee.
就是一种饭
It has soup, vegetables, and rice in it.
里面有汤 有菜 还有饭
It's hot and soft.
热热的 软软的
My brother and dad
我哥哥和爸爸
make delicious vegetable congee.
做得特别好吃
I want you to eat with us,
想留你在我们家吃饭
OK?
好不好
OK.
好
Thank you, sister.
谢谢珉敏姐姐
If you're alone
你要是一个人
and have nowhere to go,
没有地方去的话
come join us.
也一起吧
Do I have to hold your hand, too?
你也要我牵着才会走啊
Thank you, sister.
谢谢珉敏姐姐
You are welcome.
真乖
Mr. Xiang,
向警官
has anyone said
有没有人说
you look like
你长得特别像
a movie star?
一个电影明星
No.
没有
The movie star...
就那个
Wait a minute.
你等我一下
Mr. Xiang, pardon her.
向警官 别介意啊
That's how my sister is.
我妹妹这人就这样
[I got it.]
找到了 找到了
Clark Gable.
克拉克·盖博
Check this out.
你看看这跟你哥
Does he look like your brother?
长得像不像
My brother looks way better than him.
我哥哥比他好看多了
No way.
怎么会
Check it out.
你看像不像
Come on.
像什么像
They look nothing alike.
一点儿也不像
No way.
怎么可能
Look at his eyes.
这眼睛
His nose.
这鼻子
His mouth.
这嘴巴
And his temperament.
还有这气质
Aren't they exactly the same?
不一模一样吗
Sit down. Don't be silly.
坐下吧 丢人
Come on.
快
[Did you attend the accounting class]
我给你报的那会计班
[I signed up for you?]
你去了吗
[I did.]
我去了
[But I don't understand the lesson.]
但是我没太听懂
What's the teacher's last name?
那老师姓什么
I don't know.
我不知道
You've taken a class.
你说你这上了半天课吧
But you don't know
老师姓什么
the teacher's name.
你都不知道
He said his name. But I forgot it.
他说了 我没记住
When I came out of the class,
但是我从那会计班出来
I saw a fish seller there.
看门口有个卖鱼的
The fish was big and fresh.
又大又新鲜
So I bought one.
我就买了一条回来烧
This is it.
就是这条
My lesson is not in vain, anyway.
也不算白去啊
Brother, good for you.
哥 你真棒
Let's eat.
赶快吃饭 吃饭
Help yourself.
快快快
The fish looks delicious.
这条鱼看着好好吃啊
Here.
来
Let me serve you some.
姐姐给你夹一块儿啊
Have a piece without bones.
吃一块儿没刺的
Have some cauliflower.
再吃个菜花
Is it salty?
咸不咸
No.
不咸
That's good.
不咸就行
Do you like
你喜欢吃
my brother's cooking?
我哥哥做的菜啊
Yes.
喜欢
Let's eat.
来 动手吧
Come on.
吃吃吃
[It's not bad.]
还行
What's your name?
你叫什么名字啊
My name is Li Qiushi.
我叫黎秋实
What grade are you in?
读几年级啊
Second grade.
小学二年级
At this age,
这个年纪啊
you should study hard.
好好读书就对了
What about you?
你呢
Did you ever go to school?
读过书吗
Yes.
读过
Elementary school or junior high school?
小学还是初中啊
Both.
都读过
Well,
对了
did your parents want you to be a police officer?
你父母同意你当警察吗
They don't know I'm a policeman.
他们不知道我在当警察
You kids
你们这些孩子啊
all make parents worry.
没有一个让父母省心的
How can you hide it from your parents
你说你当警察
that you are a policeman?
怎么能瞒着父母呢
Dad, how can you
爸 你怎么连客人
lecture our guest?
一起教训啊
Because he is just like you,
因为他跟你们一样
worrying his parents.
不让父母省心
Well...
那个 那个 那个
These are the eggs
这个是我今天早上买的
I bought this morning.
买的那个鸡蛋
Only this little girl
就这个小丫头
is good.
乖一点儿
That doesn't stop you
那你还不是喜欢我们
from loving your children.
喜欢得不得了
I didn't say that.
我刚刚又没说话
Did I?
我说了吗
I didn't.
我又没说
You don't have to tell us.
你不说我们也知道啊
Right, Luo Minmin?
是吧 骆珉敏
Luo Minmin?
骆珉敏
Don't you dare call me by my name.
骆珉敏是你叫的吗
Call me Sister.
叫姐姐
Names
人起名字
are meant to be called.
不就是用来叫的吗
I want to call you Luo Minmin.
我就叫骆珉敏
Luo Minmin.
骆珉敏 骆珉敏
Don't you dare stand up.
你还敢站起来
How dare you?
你厉害了你
What can you do about it?
怎么了
You are disrespectful little thing.
没大没小
This is my home too.
这也是我家
Why can't I call you by name?
我凭什么不能叫
How dare you bang on the table?
还敢拍桌子
Do you want to be beaten?
是不是欠揍
Do you still want to eat?
你这饭还想不想吃了
What's wrong with you?
你怎么了
Do you want to hit me again?
你又想打我是吗
Who hit you?
谁打你了
You are done.
你完蛋了
I tell you.
我告诉你
I won't let you eat.
这顿饭你也别想吃了
Enough.
好好好 行行行
There are so many dishes.
你说这么多菜
Why can't you eat in peace?
都堵不上你们的嘴啊
He meant you.
说你呢
Sit down.
快点儿坐下
Caution.
躲着点儿
Make room for me.
给我腾个地儿
It's hot.
烫烫烫
Here comes the vegetable congee.
菜泡饭来喽
This is the vegetable congee.
这就是菜泡饭啊
Come on, have a taste.
来 快尝尝 快尝尝
Thank you, sir.
谢谢伯伯
Mr. Xiang,
向警官
let me serve you a bowl.
我也给你盛一碗
Thanks.
谢谢
What do you want to say?
有话说
Serve me a bowl.
给我盛
Don't you have hands?
你自己没手啊
Do it.
快点儿的
Do it yourself.
自己盛
Serve me a bowl.
给我盛
You serve her a bowl.
你给她盛
I'll do it.
我 我给盛 我给盛
What a troublemaker.
一天天的不让人省心
How could take to the street?
你看你还上街游行
Didn't you know how worried dad was?
爸都担心成什么样了
If you get caught,
回头被人抓了
what do we do?
你看我们怎么办
Dad didn't want you to be a policewoman.
爸还不让你当警察呢
But you became a police anyway.
你还不是也去
Why didn't you listen to dad?
你怎么不听爸的话呢
I became a policewoman...
我当警察
What did I become a policewoman for?
我当警察为什么
It's all about
还不是为了
protecting our family.
保护我们家吗
Don't give me big words.
说大道理
You always have a point.
你说什么道理你都有
That's because I have a point.
那是因为我有道理
That's what you think.
那是你觉得
You still want to talk.
你还要说话
Why can't I...
我 我怎么
Why can't I talk?
我 我为什么不能说话
You went to an accounting class,
你一个去学会计
ending up buying a fish home,
你买条鱼回来
Is it reasonable?
你像话吗
If I didn't buy that fish,
那我不买鱼
what would you eat today?
你今天你吃啥呀你
These are the clothes
这是我小时候
I wore when I was a kid.
穿过的衣服
These fit Qiushi.
秋实穿着大小刚好合适
Those clothes you gave her
你给她的那些衣服
are too big for her.
都太大了
You also have moments
你也有像小孩子一样
acting up like a child.
做不好事情的时候
Qiushi,
秋实
I probably won't be
以后姐姐可能
a policewoman anymore.
就当不了警察了
But if there's anything
不过你要是
you don't understand,
有什么不懂的问题
come to me at this photo shop.
就来这间照相铺子找我
OK?
好不好
I got it, sister.
知道了珉敏姐姐
Thank you.
谢谢你
Ms. Luo,
骆警官
thank your family for your hospitality.
谢谢你们一家人的款待
Don't worry. You will not be suspended.
你就安心当警察吧
The problems of the Fourth Station House,
四所的事儿
it will be solved.
会解决的
Remember to drink the milk before sleep.
睡觉前记得把牛奶喝了
Ms. Minmin asked me
这是珉敏姐姐
to give you this.
让我给你的
This is the money for that day's mission.
那天执行任务的经费
She told me not to take it out
她说我一定要
before you get home.
等你回家再拿出来
In case you refuse to take it.
免得你不肯要
Brother,
远生哥哥
did you treat Ms. Minmin
你是不是请珉敏姐姐
to chocolate cake?
吃巧克力蛋糕了
It's our mission.
是任务
Check this out.
这写着呢
Mission funding.
任务经费
Brother,
远生哥哥
I like Ms. Minmin
我特别喜欢珉敏姐姐
and her family.
还有她们一家人
Do you like her?
那你喜欢珉敏姐姐吗
Go to bed.
你赶紧睡觉
Brother,
远生哥哥
I don't want to sleep.
我不睡 不睡 不睡
Be good. Sleep.
听话啊 睡觉
[Ms. Luo,]
骆警官
[Don't worry. You will not be suspended.]
你就安心当警察吧
[The problems of the Fourth Station House,]
四所的事儿
[it will be solved.]
会解决的
[Please come in.]
请进
Do you want to see me?
有人说你找我
Are you Deng Mingyuan's contact
你是邓铭远
in Mukden?
在奉天的联络人
Yes.
是
Do you know this guy?
来 帮我认个人
Take a close look.
看清楚了
Do you know the person
照片上的这个人
in this photo?
你认识他吗
No.
不认识
Didn't Deng Mingyuan
邓铭远
ask you to contact this guy?
没有让你去联络这个人
No.
没有
What is
那邓铭远
Deng Mingyuan's plan?
到底有什么计划
All I know is that
我只知道
he was going to help
他要帮孟家夫妇
the Mengs leave Shanghai.
撤离上海
Are you talking about the Mengs
是被杀的那对
who were killed?
孟家夫妇吗
I've seen them
我之前
in Mukden before.
在奉天见过那家人
I heard they were all dead.
听说他们都死了
No.
不不不
There's a girl
有一个小女孩儿
who probably isn't dead.
可能没有死
Was it Deng Mingyuan's man
是邓铭远的人
who saved her?
把她救走了吗
Have you ever seen that man?
那个人你有没有见过
What's his name?
他叫什么名字
Is he still in Shanghai?
他现在还在不在上海
The task leader
组长
arranged a man
是安排了一个人
to protect them.
保护他们
But I don't know who they are.
但是我不知道是谁
The leader
组长
never tells me things like that.
他是不会告诉我这些的
Give it to me.
来人哪
[Captain,]
队长
[we've looked into it.]
我们调查过了
[In the past year,]
近一年内
[the closest person to the Mengs family]
与孟家关系最为密切的
[was Meng Duoci's French teacher.]
是孟多慈的法语老师
[She is an inspector]
她还是公董局
[of the Concession Municipal Council.]
警务处的督察员
[Her name is Shi Junyu.]
名字叫石珺昱
Mrs. Ji.
季太太
Ms. Shi, here you are.
石小姐 你来了
[Who saved Duoci?]
救多慈的是什么人啊
[Duoci said his name was Hua Zhen.]
多慈说他叫华桢
[He's from Nanjing.]
从南京来
[He's the son of]
应该是军政部次长
[Undersecretary Hua Zhuoqin.]
华卓钦的儿子
Mr. Deng entrusted him with the ticket.
邓先生把船票托付给他
At least,
至少说明
that means he's trustworthy.
他是值得信任的人
Judging by his identity,
以他的身份
he is probably not our comrade.
应该不会是我们的同志
But he is staying in Shanghai
但是他留在上海
not only to take care of Duoci
不仅照顾多慈
but also to find the murderer for her.
还承诺要帮她找到凶手
It doesn't seem like something
这又不像是一个局外人
an outsider would do.
会干的事情
I don't know
我现在也摸不清楚
who he is.
对方的底细
Maybe only Group Leader Deng
可能只有邓组长
knows who he is.
知道他的身份吧
Half a month ago,
半个月前
when Leader Deng sensed
邓组长察觉到
that Duoci's parents were in danger,
多慈的父母有危险
he had already begun to
他就已经开始动手
arrange their evacuation.
安排撤离了
But he didn't expect
但是没想到
he was late.
还是晚了一步
It has something to do with the Japanese.
凶手肯定和日本人有关
Leader Deng has been helping
邓组长一直
the Patriotic Chamber of Commerce
在帮多慈父母
chaired by Duoci's parents
成立的爱国商会
to deliver supplies to the northern front.
往北方战场运送物资
It was not until a year ago
直到一年前
that our organization in Shanghai
我们上海的组织
was completely destroyed,
被彻底破坏
and the Japanese kept sending spies
日本人又不断从北方
from the north to Shanghai
派间谍来上海
to search for those involved in the plan.
搜捕跟计划有关的人
That is why ISKRA was abolished.
依斯克拉才被迫中止
I suspect that the Japanese
我现在怀疑
are not just targeting
日本人的目标
Duoci's parents.
不止是多慈父母
Regardless of
所以不管华桢的底细
Hua Zhen's background,
到底是什么样的
when it comes to finding the murderer,
在找凶手这件事情上
his goal is the same as ours.
我们的目标是一致的
In the notorious Purge a year ago,
一年前的清扫行动
we lost all of
我们的机务员和译电员
our operators and interpreters.
都牺牲了
You were
你本来是我们
the best telegrapher.
最好的电报员
But now,
可现在
you're part of action team.
也变成了行动队员了
Leader Deng
邓组长以前
used to joke
总是开玩笑说
that we are short of talent.
我们是八个茶碗六个盖
We go wherever we are needed.
哪里需要哪里派
I'm trying to fix
当时他拼死
the telegraph transmitter
保护下来的发报机
he risked his life to protect.
我现在在想办法维修
We don't have a telegraph transmitter.
没有收报机
But I'm working on the radio.
我也买了收音机在改装
I am ready
总之我随时做好
to be a telegrapher at any time.
重回电台的准备
Unless the organization tell me to,
但是在组织召唤我之前
I'll go wherever I'm needed.
我就是一个茶碗盖
Leader Deng was arrested.
邓组长被捕
There are only three people left
我们的小组
in our group, you, me,
就只剩下你 我
and Zhang.
还有老张三个人
Tread carefully.
万事小心
With the identity of an inspector
我有督察员的身份
as disguise,
做掩护
I can move freely.
行动还是便利的
Don't worry.
放心吧
This is the office of the Police Service
公董局警务处
of the Concession Municipal Council.
总部办公室
This is Shi Junyu.
我是石珺昱
[We found the traitor in Mukden.]
奉天的叛徒找到了
Don't move.
不许动 不许动
Get down.
蹲下
Get down. Don't move.
蹲下 不许动
Inspector Shi,
石督察
the director said
总监说了
he wanted to take your car
待会儿跟您的车
back to the Concession Municipal Council.
回公董局
Noted.
知道了
Thanks. Are you going in?
谢谢 你进去吗
I'll gas up the car and be right back.
我给车加了油就回来
OK.
好的
Inspector Shi.
石珺昱督察
You must be Inspector Shi, Miss Shi.
您就是石督察石小姐吧
May I have your name?
您是
Nice to meet you.
您好
I am Wei Daiqing.
鄙人魏岱擎
I'm the head of the investigation team
是淞沪警备司令部
of Shanghai Garrison Command.
侦查队队长
Sorry to bother you.
打扰了
I have something to ask you.
有点小事想向您请教
I'm sorry.
不好意思
It's not a good time.
我现在不方便
Let's take a rain check.
换个时间吧
I only have a few questions.
就几句话的工夫
If it is really inconvenient for you,
您要是实在不方便的话
we can talk here.
我们就可以在这儿聊
It won't take long.
耽误不了多长时间的
It's our first meeting.
我们第一次见面
Don't you think it's too abrupt,
魏队长不觉得
Mr. Wei?
这样实在太唐突了吗
Agreed.
是
I'm here for the Mengs murder case.
我是为孟家凶杀案来的
I found out
我查到
that Miss Shi is
石小姐是
Miss Meng Duoci's French teacher.
孟多慈小姐的法文老师
I think
我想
maybe you're
或许您
more concerned about
比我更关心孟多慈小姐
Miss Meng Duoci's safety than I am.
现在的安危吧